Everyone, today I'm going to take you
to a really cool place where
you can recycle seven plastic bottles
and make a piece of clothing
. This is something that
netizens have been wanting us to film for a long time,
so today
we're serious about picking up the pieces
and showing everyone
the textile industry in Changhua.
Let's On
the day of filming,
the factory machines were running at full capacity,
and the sounds of the machines provided the most authentic production atmosphere.
So, after filming, we decided to
return to the studio
to re-post-produce and re-dub the video
for everyone to see.
Welcome to
Taiwan's Changhua
Textile Industry
. Taiwan's textile industry is truly impressive,
whether it's fabrics, functional fabrics,
sweatshirts
, or even all sorts of other
unusual clothing you can't imagine.
Many of these fabrics are exported worldwide,
and today I'm going to tell you something
quite unique : how
you can make a brand new piece of clothing
out of seven plastic bottles.
Do you know how impressive Taiwan's fabric making
is? I'm not talking about plastics,
of course, it can't
compare to Southeast Asia or mainland China
, but Taiwan's functional fabrics
hold over 50% of
the global market share.
Wow, that's a lot!
Over 50%!
Taiwan
is truly impressive
in the field of functional fabrics , especially
for outdoor brands.
Do you know what percentage Taiwan holds?
I'm talking about the entire world,
70% .
That's a lot!
70%. It's actually
quite impressive.
You must find it hard to imagine, right?
In the past, we imagined
dyeing
or fabric manufacturing
as highly polluting and labor-intensive
, or family-run factories where
they slowly threaded
warp
and weft with a shuttle to weave fabric. Fabrics
without functionality are different.
Taiwan is one of the few countries that's
quite advanced in polyester recycling and
fabric
research and development
. So today, let's start with a basic concept
: plastic bottles.
Plastic bottles are called PET.
People in the industry call it PET
. How many kL is your PET? Is your PET pure?
PET's scientific name in Chinese is
polyethylene terephthalate,
right? It's quite difficult,
the chemistry is quite difficult,
and
it's generally called PET.
PET is
the most common material many of us use
when recycling plastic bottles.
But it's not the only thing that can be recycled.
In fact, many things can be recycled . It's
just that the recycling of plastic bottles
is relatively mature
in the recycling industry
. So if you can imagine
more applications for recycling,
you can start small and grow up to make a fortune.
So usually, after drinking beverages
or mineral water in plastic bottles,
we will throw them into the recycling room
or the resource recycling truck,
right? It goes through several steps
. The first is sorting,
because there are different numbers on the back.
Then there are colors.
Even PET
has different colors.
After cleaning the bottle caps,
the first major step
is crushing.
In fact, crushing is a very important step.
Basically, in all industrial production
and recycling mechanisms,
most people usually use crushing,
whether it's recycled metal or recycled materials.
When you want to
remelt and remake something,
we often use crushing.
Otherwise, imagine
if you were to use plastic bottles to make clothes today,
would they look like this?
Plastic bottle clothes are difficult to move, right?
And they are very sharp, so no one will buy them.
So usually we return them to
their original raw material
, PET. After RPET is crushed
, it will become small particles.
When you pick it up with your hands, it will feel like this.
These are actually
clean fragments that
have been selected.
So, many 3C
products that are updated every year
can be
crushed and recycled in this way.
But first of all, your material
must be pure and clean so that it will not
be contaminated by a lot of things
when it is crushed,
and it cannot be re-melted and re-made.
This is a basic concept.
Of course, you can't start using it after it is crushed
. Usually, we still need to
clean it, pump out water, and dry it
, and then use a strong magnet
to absorb the impurities.
But you must think that the strong magnet
is like using a magnet to absorb it.
This is the principle of mechanical design.
When you drop your crushed materials down, you can
see these small sticks on top.
They actually have magnets inside.
Because sometimes
people will stuff things into plastic bottles,
or they may be attached to them
, or when there are a lot of debris,
they may stick to them.
You can use a strong magnet in the middle
to absorb some impurities,
so that your material will be pure.
Then, basically,
when these materials are clean,
you can melt them.
Melting is actually a kind of heating.
Heat it to make it soft
so that it sticks together.
Have you ever eaten
Japanese flowing noodles?
It's like this flowing noodles.
We will take the
melted PET
and turn it into noodles.
After melting, it becomes small noodles.
Next, we need to do another thing,
which is granulation.
Because the material is now clean
and becomes sticks.
Have you ever seen
people making candies as a child
and
then cutting it...
cutting it into pieces?
So granulation is actually the same thing.
Why do we cut it into pieces?
First, it is easier to store
because it
is not easy to roll noodles.
Then,
it can be sold as material to others
, or it
will be more convenient for the next step.
Do you remember
when we were in India, we saw people injecting things?
We injected the helmets.
The material is actually one by one.
In
the injection molding machine,
the granular raw materials
are usually the best to use.
So after that, you put
these particles into this small barrel.
You think it is only this small,
but it is not.
This is also
the entire copper barrel. The entire chimney
is filled with granulated particles.
This is a large factory.
Next, these small particles
will enter the molten state again.
The black things inside
are actually masterbatches
. The colors they emit
can be adjusted
with these different masterbatches
. Have you ever used a
shower head at home?
You can imagine that
it has melted and
turned into a liquid.
Then, when it comes out of your shower head,
it will spray out like a shower.
The concept
is that the motors on it will
squeeze out these molten particles
through pressure ,
and it will not break.
It is like a line,
so it is divided into
12, 36, and 72 strands, which
are all kinds of different strands
, but in the end it becomes
You must be wondering what this strand is, right? When
we describe fibers, we usually
say this.
Look, this is a line, right?
But if you look at the end of the line,
it is divided into
many strands...
When we talk about making textiles and fibers,
we call this a strand.
Now you have the concept of a strand and a line, right?
So, then you have to enter
the automatic doffing machine.
The automatic doffing machine is
to divide these materials,
the original plastic bottles,
the original small particles,
and the strands after being melted
into strands again,
and finally become a line.
How do
you collect this line? After collecting it
, it is rolled into a roll.
That's it. A roll of thread.
So now you see humans making a thread.
No matter if you watch wilderness survival channels,
you will see people
taking plant vines
, stripping them into silk
, and then rolling them up like this.
It is actually the same concept, which
is to weave different strands
into a thread
to make it a strong thread.
So after the previous steps,
you will make two kinds of threads.
You can think of them as
finished products and semi-finished
products. The so-called finished product
means that it can be used directly,
for example, it can be used to make some
blackout cloth,
windbreakers,
and some fabrics for outdoor products.
The other semi-finished product
means that it needs to be processed again
. The two threads
look different.
One is loose and
the other is like noodles. No,
the two are different.
This one, which
has not been false-twisted
, is called a semi-finished product.
So you see, although its lines
look shiny
, when I pull them,
they actually have no tension
. When I tighten it and then pull it,
there is no tension and no elasticity.
But the other line that has been false-twisted,
you see, I tighten it as well.
Do you find
that it feels
like a shock absorber?
It looks very fluffy, like permed hair, just like
when you were a kid, did you use corn silk
to curl your hair?
After curling, it will have elasticity,
so your clothes
will be comfortable to wear and will become fluffy.
So, think about
something hard like a plastic bottle.
Once it is false-twisted, The correct processing
makes it still very fluffy when worn.
What is the concept of false twist? I tell you
, you are lucky to meet me today.
The concept of false twist is that you can imagine that
this is a thread.
False twist means turning it in the clockwise direction
and the counter-clockwise direction.
After turning it like this,
it becomes tight, right?
After it is tightened, turn
it back and it becomes fluffy,
but it is still the same.
Its inner bones
have been sorted out, you know.
And the false twist machine room is very spectacular.
It grows like this
, and the whole picture you see now
is actually like a cycle
. It starts from this side
and goes up,
then goes down,
and then goes back
to become the bundle of threads
you see now
. Why does it have to run a full circle
? In fact, the most critical part is this needle.
This needle basically rotates tens of thousands of times per minute
, and it spins
like crazy like this ,
and then twists your thread again.
And you see this other area
of ​​shiny yarn.
This is the wedding veil that you girls want to wear
when you get married.
Why does the wedding veil look
so shiny? It is because it
has been processed into shiny yarn
during the production process.
So you see, it looks very cool under the light
. So when you wear clothes normally,
you will not think about
the huge equipment behind it
, which helps you weave the threads one by one
, and finally it becomes clothes
, but it is still far from being clothes
because After finishing this step,
they actually have to go to the most serious,
tragic and cruel place
, which is QC. QC
is not done after the clothes are finished,
but QC is done on the online part. Because I produce
thousands or tens of thousands of
thread bundles at a time
before they are slowly woven into cloth, and
the cloth is counted in batches and bundles,
so they will weave these threads
into the shape of a sock,
very similar to the socks with pullovers,
and then go into the dyeing room
to be dyed into a special color.
Then you see,
when you pass it through the sock,
you will see different color levels,
right? It looks a little different.
If it looks different,
then all of them will be rejected
because if they send it abroad
and find that the color level is too different
or if it is sent to If the quality is not good abroad,
not just the bundle will be picked out,
but the entire container will be returned. It's
terrible, and
you even have to pay for the shipping fee yourself.
Okay, now
you know how to make the thread
, but it's still a long way
from making your clothes or your piece of cloth.
First of all, you have to understand the longitude and latitude.
Have you heard of longitude
and latitude ?
The longitude and latitude
of the earth.
In fact, when we talk about cloth, we will talk about the longitude and latitude.
So when you start to make a piece of cloth,
you have to go through the warping. The warping
is very spectacular
. You take the bundles of thread you just made
, and then you arrange them neatly
into a line array,
just like this.
Have
you seen Dongfang Bubai? Do you know Dongfang Bubai?
I don't know
if it's from your era.
What is
Dongfang Bubai? It's about thread.
Snap, a whole row of threads.
No one knows.
Haven't you read Jin Yong?
People nowadays don't read Jin Yong.
Anyway, there is a person
whose trick is to shoot out a thread array
like warping . The key
is to control the tension of each thread very well
when pulling out the thread array.
That is the adjustment of the machine
. If the tension is not pulled well
, then when you are weaving,
you will see that the cloth is crooked,
or it will break easily.
This is very subtle but very important.
But usually no one knows.
After the threads are arranged,
we have to go through a step
called sizing
. Sizing can be imagined as sizing clothes.
There are many kinds of sizing materials
. In the old days, people called it white glue
, or they can put some
coatings on your threads.
So you When you first get the clothes,
do you feel that they are very stiff? The clothes are very stiff
and look a little shiny .
After a few washes in the washing machine,
your clothes will become more and more worn and wrinkled.
In fact, one benefit of starching
is that it can increase the friction of the clothes
and make them more durable.
Therefore, starching is usually used
. Next, your PET bottle fabric
has been processed to 50%.
After this step,
we will proceed to
warp stitching. You have the concept of warp. Then
, warp stitching is to stitch two different warp threads
together.
Sometimes its purpose is to match
colors
, make the clothes have layers,
or color or pattern.
It will go through the warp stitching action.
Next, the next action is
It needs to be divided into upper and lower layers
, which is called Lingqu.
Why Lingqu?
It is to make it easier to weave in the heddle.
Why weave
in the heddle? Weaving in the heddle is to allow your cloth
to find the front part of your front.
At this time,
you can decide whether your cloth
should be plain woven, twill, or patterned. You
have to make a decision
at this step. Then, according to
the pattern designed for each cloth,
each warp yarn will
be inserted into the needle eye in the reed and heddle. It
is very complicated, isn't it?
It is unexpected that from the loom cloth farmers
to the present, weaving has
developed to its current state.
So you can see
why some people's
cloth itself has different patterns,
different colors, and different layers
or Some functional fabrics
will have features such as breathable inside, heat dissipation outside, and
sweat absorption inside.
After going through
all these steps,
you will be able to make
the fabric and clothing style
you have designed in your mind.
Next, we will start weaving. When you
were a child, have you ever heard the Three Character
Classic? Human nature is inherently
good, and natures are similar. Habits
tend to separate us, etc. But the most important part is "If
a child does not learn, he will break the loom."
Do you know
who the person who breaks the loom
in the Three Character Classic
is? It is Mencius' mother, Meng Mu.
So how serious is breaking the loom
? When we have just gone through
so many steps,
Meng Mu suddenly appeared in this factory.
So how do you cut all
the warp threads you have just arranged ?
How serious is it? This is too
serious
.
This is what the ancients called "breaking the shuttle."
I always thought that breaking the shuttle
meant breaking the machine,
not the machine.
Although you know,
in the past, Chinese teachers talked about breaking the shuttle
. The shuttle is actually the shuttle.
We just said that it is the straight warp.
Then we tie a weft on
the shuttle
and pass it through.
Then you will take something that looks like a ruler.
So in the past, people said breaking the shuttle
means breaking the shuttle.
The Chinese meaning is like this,
but I tell you, when I was learning to weave,
the teacher didn't mean it.
The breaking the shuttle is like
in many cartoons.
Meng Mu cuts the warp
.
If the warp is cut,
the whole piece of cloth is useless
because you break the shuttle. The cloth can still be used.
She can warp it once. No,
it can't be warped
because warping means you
warp it straight like this, back and forth once.
If it breaks, there's no way to straighten it back again, which is
a waste of work
. So, actually, my Chinese teacher
and my weaving teacher
said two completely different versions.
Usually, according to industrial production,
I believe the version the weaving teacher said
, which is to cut the warp.
But the key is that
you have to learn it well, otherwise I will be angry.
No matter in industrial production,
if she wants to go all out,
she will definitely cut the warp.
That's how I let my son know that
your grandmother shouldn't do it anymore.
It's up for discussion. There are official history and unofficial history.
So now we have straight lines,
but a piece of clothing
doesn't only have Straight lines,
so at this time you need to use the weft
and weave it horizontally into a piece of cloth
, just weave it into cloth like this,
it's not like this
, so at this time the warp and weft come in,
we need to enter the weft part.
There are actually two
ways to transmit the weft.
One of them was to use water
to shoot it with water,
just like Blastoise,
just
use the power of water to shoot your weft
through,
and then the one that bounces back in the middle
is called a heddle.
Imagine that
I have a straight warp
in front of me, and
now when the weft passes through,
I need a heddle
to bring it back,
otherwise the line will be scattered in the middle,
so Blastoise shoots once
and then bounces back once.
Shoot once, hit back once
, shoot once, hit back once.
In the past, with traditional looms,
we would take a shuttle
and throw it
forward.
Whoosh, whoosh, whoosh, whoosh .
Now, because of the advancement of air compressors
and our
precision pneumatic components
, we can now use air jets
to thread the needle. Just like that, puff, puff, puff. Finally,
after the warp and weft are interwoven on both sides,
the piece of cloth woven by the Cowherd and the Weaver Girl
is finally completed
. Did you know that the Weaver Girl weaves cloth?
Nonsense
, did you know that
the Cowherd sells cattle? The Cowherd chops trees .
How could it be that the Cowherd doesn't chop trees ?
The Cowherd doesn't chop trees. The Cowherd herds cattle.
Then who
chops trees
?
Wu Gang,
Wu Gang chops trees, right?
So, look at that.
A piece of clothing is just like that.
What you think is a small recycling process
is actually happening behind the scenes
in the invisible factory.
There is a huge production chain
that helps you recycle
and reuse it.
So when you see some clothes marked
as made of recycled polyester,
there are actually many
mechanical engineers
, equipment manufacturers,
and R&D people who
have tried every possible way to improve
the traditional
weaving process
into this
huge Taiwanese weaving industry. It
is very great and powerful.
But why do we do this?
Because the cost of doing this
is relatively high.
In fact, it is all to get rid of
petrochemicals. The demand of the production chain,
like the factory we filmed
, actually helps
a lot of very large
production chains that everyone has at their disposal
to supply their products and fabrics.
Therefore, these very large companies
will stipulate that your production process and your
factory
must have recycled machines
ESG
in order to supply
all the product lines and materials of
their company and brand. Although
many of the scenes and factory equipment in our video today
are generally inaccessible,
you still think these devices are very cool
and these ideas are really amazing and dazzling.
In fact, I would recommend that you
go to the upcoming
Taiwan Design Exhibition.
You know, this year 2025
Where is Taiwan's largest design exhibition in
Changhua this year
? It's October 10th to 26th.
I'll be there giving a presentation
, and
I'll
be there. You
can take the high-speed rail,
no matter where you are in the city or county,
and go directly to the exhibition hall next to the
Tianzhong High Speed ​​Rail Station.
It's called the Changnan Exhibition Area
. The theme
of this exhibition hall is Changhua Power
. Why is it called that?
Because they want to showcase the connection between Changhua's industries
and the world's industries—the Changhua energy.
In
addition to the many amazing Changhua factories shown in this video,
there will also be many things
like light and sound shows, immersive experiences
, and many things you may never have known about Changhua
, connected by amazing
Changhua companies
. Made in China Changhua
will show you the true strength of Changhua manufacturing
. Okay, this episode is the long-awaited
special on how Taiwan's textile industry can make a fortune through recycling.
I hope you like it.
If you'd like to know more
about quirky industrial knowledge
or any other unique industries,
please leave a comment below.
Or you can save the cost of a drink every month and
join our super-serious membership.
In addition to getting many
interesting group buy items every month
, you can also watch many
videos that others can't see.
This is Super-serious Boy.
See you next week. Bye.
Wu Gang
chops trees, and the Cowherd herds cattle. The Weaver Girl
weaves cloth.
So, the Mid-Autumn Festival is
about Wu Gang
chopping trees
and the Jade Rabbit pounding medicine.
The one up there isn't the Weaver Girl
, but Chang'e.
Chang'e flies to the moon.
On the moon, there's the Weaver Girl
and there's Chang'e
. The one going up
there to find the girl
is Wu Gang
and the Cowherd
, not
Wu Gang. He was already on the moon,
but I don't know why
he didn't go up there.
Okay, it doesn't matter.